Finding Aid for Science Research Club (University of Michigan) records, 1902-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Science Research Club (University of Michigan) Records 1902-2004, 1940-1988
Science Research Club (University of Michigan)
3.75 linear feet
87318 Bimu M1 2
University of Michigan organization founded by graduate students in 1902 as the Junior Research Club to promote exchange of ideas among those active in pure or applied scientific investigation. Records document founding and development of the club, include club histories, minute books, financial records, membership statistics ad meeting programs.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Accession No. 4596
The record group is open for research.
The Science Research Club of the University of Michigan was formed on October 20, 1902 by roughly thirty graduate students in the Pathological Laboratory. The initial name was the Michigan Laboratory Club, but this was quickly changed to the Junior Research Club. This name remained unchanged until 1945 when it adopted its current name, the Science Research Club. The club's first president, Louis M. Gelston, was also one of its founders. The club has had some stellar members including Jonas E. Salk of Polio vaccine fame and Donald A. Glaser, who was awarded a Nobel prize for his work in physics.
The club's purpose was clearly established in the original constitution: "The purpose of this organization shall be to establish and maintain an association which shall permit persons active in pure or applied scientific investigation to obtain the stimulus of mutual contact and the benefits of interchange of ideas."
Activities take place during the academic year. The meetings commence on the first Tuesday of the month, and generally consist of two scientific presentations followed by brief discussions. The last meeting of the year is a banquet where officers are introduced for the following year. It had been the tradition of the club to meet in the Rackham Amphitheater. This tradition changed on November 3, 1970 when the organization decided to move its meetings to the Chrysler Center Auditorium.
In January 1969 the club discussed the possibility of admitting women to membership. In a close vote the motion was rejected. In January 1972 another motion to allow women to become members was offered and adopted by the members. As a consequence of this vote the constitution of the club was changed in March 1972 to reflect a non-biased membership policy. The club was dissolved in 2004 due to a lack of active members and volunteers for officer positions.
The records of the Science Research Club measure 3.75 linear feet. The dates of coverage stretch from 1902 to 2004, with the bulk dates covering the years from 1940 to 1988. The records have been divided into six series: Background and Organization; Record Books; Financial Records; Officers and Committees; Programs; and Membership.
Subjects:
Junior Research Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.; Science Research Club (University of Michigan); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women in science--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Background and Organization
  The Background and Organization series contains a concise history by A.D. Moore (up to 1980), along with a host of club memorabilia including such things as a list of past officers, pamphlets, clippings, and obituaries of former members. Club statistics are also included, the majority of which are on the early years of the club. Statistics document such membership categories as new members, percentage of new members, membership withdrawn, withdrawal percentages, and dues paying members. This series also series deals with the club's constitutions and amendments and contains various copies of the club's constitution as it was changed and amended over the years. Background and Organization also contains a file on the final meeting of the club in 2004 and a scattering of administrative materials (1985-2003), which includes agendas, meeting minutes, and room reservations for events.
  - Club History 1902-2004 (Box 1)
  - Club Statistics 1926-1946 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and Amendments 1931-1988 (Box 1)
  - Final Meeting 2004 (Box 1)
    (includes agenda and comments by Anne S. Benninghoff)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative Materials 1985-2003 (Box 1)
    (includes minutes, agendas, and room reservations)
- Record Books
  The Record Books series documents the activities of the club in segments. The first book covers the time period 1902-1914. Included with the general information (banquet programs, financial reports, membership lists, minutes of meetings) are pertinent writings that elucidate the early history (1902-1906) of the club, e.g, the first constitution (1902). The second record book (1914-1932) primarily covers conventional club information. The third book documents club activities the time period 1932-1941. In this era the club considered some policy changes dealing with new members. The fourth book covers the years from 1941 to 1945. The fifth (1958-1980) book chronicles two major changes in the club including a new meeting place (Chrysler Center 1970) and the acceptance of female members (1972).
  - 1902-1914 (Box 1)
  - 1914-1932 (Box 1)
  - 1932-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1980 (Box 1)
- Financial Records
  Along with the bound Record Books, there is a series, Financial Records dated 1924-1962 that encompasses the financial records of the club. It includes a bound volume titled, "The Science Research Club of the University of Michigan." Although the title of the financial records volume suggests an end date of 1965, records are present only through 1962. There are also several folders of financial records (1941-2001), including information on the Robert Ruthruff Trust (1984-1999)
  - 1924-1962 (ledger book) (Box 1)
  - 1941-1983 (Box 1)
  - 1984-1993 (Box 1)
  - 1995-2001 (Box 1)
  - Robert Ruthruff Trust 1984-1999 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Officers and Committees
  The series Officers and Committees contains (1.0 linear foot) detailing the administrations and their committees from 1931 to 1988. Included in this series are 44 folders that contain yearly lists of current officers. The records also contain information on committee activities including reports of the silent secretary, programs and financial statements.
  - 1931-1955/1956, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - 1956/1957-1987/1988, 29 folders (Box 2)
- Programs (including Banquet)
  The Programs series measures (1.0 linear foot) covering most years between 1902 and 2004. The series includes individual and yearly programs, correspondence, publicity, and speaker questionnaires. The programs detail the speakers and topics for any given meeting or year of meetings. Programs for the annual banquet are included.
  - General Correspondence 1975-2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - List of Programs 1902-1986 (Box 2)
  - Publicity 1988-2004 (with gaps) (Box 2)
  - Speaker Questionnaire 1988-1989, 1995-1999 (Box 2)
  - Speaker Suggestions 1988-1990, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Thank You Letters 1986-2004 (Box 2)
  - 1936-1983, 44 folders
  - 1984-2004, 22 folders (Box 3)
- Membership
  Membership, the final series (1.0 linear foot) includes a comprehensive list of all members from 1902 to 1959, and lists for most years from 1927 through 1987. Also included are membership nominations materials, 1942-1983, membership questionnaires, membership units, a log of members and guests (1995-2004), and a survey of the membership. Of particular interest are the 1972 questionnaires dealing with the admission of women into the organization.
  - Questionnaires re: revision of membership code and constitution) 1934-1935 (Box 3)
  - Questionnaires (re: membership for women) 1972 (Box 3)
  - Survey of "Values Derived from Attendance" 1980-2004 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Membership Applications undated (Box 3)
  - Membership Application Forms 1985-1998 (Box 3)
  - Membership Units 1960-1967 (Box 3)
    (categories from which new members could be nominated)
  - Membership Lists
    - 1902-1959 (master list) (Box 3)
    - 1927-1987, 19 folders (Box 3)
  - Membership Nominations
    - 1942-1948, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1949-1983 (some gaps), 21 folders (Box 4)
  - Log of Members and Guests 1995-2004 (Box 4)